Philip Leslie Hale
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Philip Leslie Hale papers
1818-1962 (bulk 1877-1939)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Philip Leslie Hale
6.7 linear feet
The papers of Boston painter, teacher, critic, and writer Philip Leslie Hale measure 6.7 linear feet and are dated 1818-1962 (bulk dates 1877-1939). Biographical information, correspondence, artwork, writings, printed material, and photographs document the artist's career and personal life. The collection also includes research materials and catalogs compiled by Albert J. Kennedy for a never-published Philip Leslie Hale memorial volume.
Biographical Note
Philip Leslie Hale was the son of prominent Unitarian minister and well-known author, Edward Everett Hale. Members of this distinguished old Boston family included such ancestors as Revolutionary War hero Nathan Hale, influential preacher Lyman Beecher, educator Catherine Beecher, and Harriet Beecher Stowe, author of Uncle Tom's Cabin. From a young age Philip's talent and interest in drawing was encouraged by his parents, especially his mother. An older artist sister, Ellen Day Hale (1855-1940) and an aunt, Susan Hale (1834-1910), a trained painter, provided Philip with his first art lessons.
Family tradition and expectations decreed that after completing studies at the Boston Latin School and Roxbury Latin School, Hale would attend Harvard. After passing Harvard's entrance examination, as required by his father, Philip was free to pursue art. He enrolled in the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, in the fall of 1883, where he was an early pupil of Edmund C. Tarbell. The following year he continued his studies in New York at the Art Students League under J. Alden Weir and Kenyon Cox.
In early 1887, Hale went to Paris, adopted a bohemian lifestyle, and studied at the École des Beaux-Arts and the Académie Julian. He became friends with fellow students Theodore Butler and William Howard ("Peggy") Hart. In the summer of 1888, the three made their first trip to Giverny, where they were among the first Americans to experiment with Impressionism. They met other American artists, including Theodore Robinson, John Leslie Breck, and Theodore Wendel, who also had been drawn to Giverny by the presence of Claude Monet. Hale returned to Boston in the summer of 1890, but was soon drawn back to Paris to be with his sweetheart Katharine Kinsella. He spent the summers of 1891-1893 continuing his experiment with Impressionism in Giverny, and during that period traveled to London, Paris, and Spain, periodically returning home and to the family's Rhode Island summer place.
In 1893 Hale began teaching cast drawing at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, where he remained on the faculty until his death in 1931. Eventually he became the chief instructor of drawing, and also offered courses in life drawing, artistic anatomy, and art history. Hale also taught at the Worcester Art Museum (1898-1910), The Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts (1913-1928), and Boston University (1926-1928).
Hale's first solo exhibition, held in 1899 at Durand-Ruel Galleries in New York City, consisted of Impressionist paintings and pastels that received mixed reviews. In subsequent years his work became increasingly academic and focused on figure paintings and portraits. He exhibited frequently in national and international shows, won numerous medals and prizes, and was elected an Associate National Academician of the National Academy of Design in 1917.
In 1902, Hale married former student, Lilian Westcott, a painter and portraitist whose success during some periods eclipsed that of her husband.
Philip Leslie Hale, like many of his relatives, was a noted writer and speaker. His column "Art in Paris" for the Canadian-based periodical Arcadia: A Journal Devoted to Music, Art and Literature, which appeared regularly between 1892 and 1893, discussed Impressionism, Post-Impressionism, and Symbolism. Hale regularly contributed art columns, reviews, and miscellaneous articles to the Boston Daily Advertiser, Boston Commonwealth, Boston Herald, and Boston Evening Transcript during the first decade of the twentieth century.
Hale's teaching stressed the importance of learning Old Master's techniques. He had a life-long interest in Vermeer, and as a writer and critic he generated quite a bit of enthusiasm for that artist among the figurative painters of the Boston School, his own students, and others. Jan Vermeer of Delft, a highly regarded monograph by Philip Leslie Hale - the first on the subject published in the United States - appeared in 1913. He wrote several other books on art subjects, and his services as a lecturer on art topics were sought after by a variety of organizations both locally and nationally.
Philip Leslie Hale died following emergency surgery in Dedham, Massachusetts, on February 2, 1931.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Boston painter, teacher, critic, and writer Philip Leslie Hale measure 6.7 linear feet and are dated 1818-1962 (bulk dates 1877-1939). Biographical information, correspondence, artwork, writings, printed material, and photographs document the artist's career and personal life. The collection also includes research materials and catalogs compiled by Albert J. Kennedy for his never-published Philip Leslie Hale memorial volume.
Biographical Information includes financial and legal records; personal documents, such as educational records, biographical notes; printed material; and notes concerning art classes and teaching. Also included are scattered letters, invitations, schoolwork, and notebooks from his youth. Ten notebooks contain sketches, along with some class notes and essays.
Family, general, and business correspondence document the personal and professional life of Philip Leslie Hale and, to a lesser extent, several of his relatives. Family correspondence includes Hale's correspondence with various relatives, and some of their correspondence with others. General correspondence with friends, colleagues and other artists is both personal and professional in nature. Correspondents include Theodore Butler, Kenyon Cox, Nancy Hale, William H. Hart, and Edmund C. Tarbell. Business correspondence concerns many aspects of Hale's career. Correspondents include students, arts institutions, models, and publishers.
Writings by Philip L. Hale consist of lectures on anatomy, art history, and various art topics; miscellaneous articles; notes on artists, esthetics and philosophy either for classroom use or his writings; character sketches, a play, poems, and political writings. Art Work by Philip L. Hale consists of 9 sketchbooks and loose sketches in pencil and ink of heads, figures, anatomical studies, landscapes, and miscellaneous subjects. A much smaller number of pastels, prints, and oil sketches are included. This series also includes a few items by other hands.
Research files and catalogs, compiled 1932-1939 by Hale's friend Albert J. Kennedy for a never-published memorial volume, include extensive correspondence and notes of interviews with friends, relatives, colleagues, former students, and models recording their reminiscences of Hale. Kennedy collected exhibition catalogs and a variety of other printed material, along with biographical and genealogical information, and photographs of Hale's work. Many of his research notes consist of handwritten transcriptions of published articles by and about Hale.
Printed Material about Philip L. Hale includes articles, reviews, and miscellaneous newspaper clippings mentioning him or containing reproductions of his work. Items by Hale consist of art reviews and miscellaneous articles on art topics, copies of his columns that appeared in Arcadia: A Journal Devoted to Music, Art and Literature, and the text of a speech.
The majority of photographs record works of art, mainly by Philip L. Hale, and also by Lilian Westcott Hale, Robert Payne, and Edmund C. Tarbell. Personal photographs include images of Hale, his relatives, and friends. Also, there are also several group portraits of the 1915 Panama-Pacific Exhibition Jury, a group portrait with students, views of Hale at work in his studio and in the classroom, pictures of a summer house, and landscapes.
Arrangement
The physical and archival arrangement of the collection does not match the order of the collection as it was microfilmed in 1964 on reels D97-D104. However, reel numbers have been noted for previously filmed material in the container listing, although the numbers may appear out of sequence.
Most series are arranged chronologically, by record type. Family and general correspondence is arranged alphabetically; business correspondence is in chronological order. Art work is arranged by medium.
Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1875-1934 (Box 1, 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1818-1944 Boxes 1-3, 2.0 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1923-1930(Boxes 3-4, 1.0 linear ft.)
Series 4: Art Work, circa 1870, 1914(Box 4, 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 5: Memorial Book, circa 1862-1962(Boxes 4-6, 8, OV 9, 2.3 linear ft.)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1886-1951(Box 6, 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1868-1928 (Box 7, 0.4 linear ft.)
Related Material
A collection of drawings by Philip Leslie Hale were loaned for microfilming in 1986 by Thomas Dunlay who had acquired them a year earlier from art dealer George Epstein. Epstein bought the drawings from Mrs. Bowers in the 1960s. The drawings are available on AAA microfilm reel 3766.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, American; Painters -- Massachusetts -- Boston; Art -- Study and teaching
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sketchbooks; Works of art; Sketches
Names:
Hart, William H., b. 1863; Kennedy, Albert J. (Albert Joseph), 1879-1968; Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919; Hale, Nancy, 1908-; Tarbell, Edmund Charles, 1862-1938; Butler, Theodore Earl, 1861-1936
Provenance
The Philip Leslie Hale papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 1962 by the artist's daughter, Nancy Hale Bowers. The majority of this gift was microfilmed on reels D97-D104. Notes by Mrs. Nathan Hale on 25 anatomy lectures by Philip Leslie Hale, and the handwritten text of an art lecture by Philip L. Hale were the gift of Lilian Westcott Hale in 1963.
Restrictions on Access
Use requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
Most of the the collection is also available on microfilm reels D97-D104 and through interlibrary loan. The current arrangement of the material, however, does not match the arrangement of microfilm.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, circa 1875-1934, Series 1:; (Box 1, 0.25 linear ft.)
  The Art Classes and Teaching folder includes school catalogs and course descriptions, assignments, exams, notes, and a few photographs. Material from Hale's juvenile years includes invitations and notes from friends and relatives and notebooks (10 vols.) that consist largely of sketches, with some class notes and essays. Financial and Legal Records are deeds and leases, insurance policies, receipts, and tax records. Personal documents consist of school records, Massachusetts State Guard discharge papers, and biographical notes.
  The Memorial Book found in Series 5: Memorial Book includes Hale Family genealogical notes and additional related items among the research files compiled by Albert J. Kennedy for his never published volume. Obituaries are filed with Series 6: Printed Material.
  - Art Classes and Teaching, 1898-1929, undated (Box 1, Reel D101)
  - Notebooks, Sketches, Invitations, 1875-1879, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel D102)
  - School Work, 1877, undated (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
  - Clubs and Meeting Notices, 1886-1922, undated (Box 1, Reel D101)
  - Exhibitors' Tickets, Museum Passes, etc., 1892-1922, undated (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
  - Financial and Legal Records, 1889-1934, undated (Box 1, Reel D102)
  - Invitations and Calling Cards, 1892-1925 (Box 1, Reel D101)
  - Juries and Prizes, 1899-1919, undated (Box 1, Reel D101)
  - Personal Documents, 1877-1929, undated (Box 1, Reel D101)
- Correspondence, circa 1818-1944, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3, 2.0 linear ft.)
  Family correspondence, 1818-1944, arranged alphabetically, includes Philip Leslie Hale's correspondence with various relatives and other family correspondence. Relatives represented are his grandfather, parents, siblings (including artist sister Ellen D. Hale), wife Lilian Westcott Hale, artist aunt Susan Hale, and several nieces and nephews writing to their grandfather Edward Everett Hale. Several correspondence files include printed items relating to the individual. Filed with the correspondence of brother Robert B. Hale are Philip's records concerning the preparation and distribution of a memorial volume.
  General Correspondence, 1889-1932, arranged alphabetically, is both personal and professional. Some of the artist friends and colleagues with whom Hale corresponded are Roswell Bacon, Frank W. Benson, James Britton, Theodore E. Butler, Ercole Cartotto, Stephen Codman, Kenyon Cox, William Howard ("Peggy") Hart, Haydon Jones, Dodge MacKnight, William MacGregor Paxton, Henry and Angee Prellwitz, Edward Redfield, and Edmund C. Tarbell. Other correspondents include Anita and Chappie Ashley, critics Philip Hale (no relation) and James Gibbons Huneker, Katharine Kinsella (with whom he was romantically involved during his time in Paris), Ethel Reed (an artist to whom he was engaged briefly), Catherine and Dora Richardson, and Maverette G. Smith.
  Business Correspondence, 1880-1935, arranged chronologically, concerns many aspects of Hale's career. Among the correspondents are current, former, and prospective students; arts institutions, including schools where he taught, and museums where Hale exhibited; models and publishers. Subjects include sales and commissions, prizes, exhibitions, packing and shipping of paintings, service on art juries, requests for lectures, and renewal of teaching appointments. There is fan mail regarding both his art and writing. A small number of personal letters, such as congratulations on his engagement, letters of condolence, and thank you notes, appears in this subseries.
  A number of illustrated letters by Philip L. Hale and other artists are included. In addition, many letters contain drawings and sketches by Philip Leslie Hale on letters sent to him that seem to have been seized upon as convenient pieces of paper.
  Additional correspondence is scattered throughout the collection. Among Series 5: Memorial Book is the research correspondence of Albert J. Kennedy who contacted many of Hale's friends, relatives, former students, models, and colleagues for the purpose of collecting their reminiscences. Series 6: Printed Material includes a small number of letters concerning Arcadia: A Journal Devoted to Music, Art and Literature filed with copies of his "Art in Paris" columns that appeared in that journal. A few letters mentioning photographs being given to Hale that were microfilmed along with Series 7: Photographs, remain filed with that series.
  The series is organized into 3 subseries:
  2.1: Family Correspondence, circa 1818-1944
  2.2: General Correspondence, circa 1887-1934
  2.3: Business Correspondence, circa 1880-1935
  - Family Correspondence, circa 1818-1944, 2.1:
    - Hale, Arthur (brother), 1875-1930, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Edward Everett (father) (Box 1, Reel D97)
      - To Various Individuals, 1852-1915, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
      - To Philip L. Hale, 1876-1909, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Edward Everett, Jr. (brother), 1885-1930, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Ellen D. (sister), 1859-1931, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Emily Perkins (mother), 1885-1914, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Herbert D. (brother), 1884-1907, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Herbert D., Jr. (nephew), 1903, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Lilian Westcott (wife), 1915-1944, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Lucretia (aunt), undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Margie (niece), 1903, undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Nancy (daughter), undated (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Nathan (grandfather), 1818 (Box 1, Reel D97)
    - Hale, Robert B. (brother) (Box 2, Reel D97-D98)
      - Correspondence, 1885-1896, undated (Box 2, Reel D97-D98)
      - Memorial Book Correspondence, 1881-1909, undated (Box 2, Reel D97-D98)
    - Hale, Susan (aunt), 1881-1909, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel D97-D98)
    - Hale, Sybil (niece), undated (Box 2, Reel D97-D98)
    - Perkins, Lucy (cousin), 1880-1899, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Westcott, Harriet Clarke (mother-in-law), 1902-1927 (Box 2, Reel D99)
  - General Correspondence, 1887-1934, undated, 2.2:
    - Ashley, Anita and Chappie, 1895-1899, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Atkinson, Carla, circa 1890-1918, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Bacon, Roswell, 1897-1902 (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Benson, Frank W., 1902-1914, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Bowditch, Katherine, 1896-1898, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Bowles, J. M., 1895-1897, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Britton, James, 1911-1934, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Butler, Theodore E. (Box 2, Reel D98)
      - Correspondence, 1887-1932, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
      - Copy Negatives and Prints of Selected Letters, undated (Box 2, Reel unfilmed)
    - Buxton, F. W, 1911-1926, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Cartotto, Ercole, 1920-1928, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Codman, Stephen, 1902, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Cox, Kenyon, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - De Carlton, Grace, 1915, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Hale, Philip (music critic; not a relative), 1907-1932, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Hart, William Howard ("Peggy"), 1893-1910, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Higginson, Ida A., 1890-1899 (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Huneker, James Gibbons, 1907, 1916, (portion not microfilmed) (Box 2, Reel D100)
    - Jones, Haydon, 1908-1925 (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Kennedy, Albert J. and Edith, undated (Box 2, Reel D98)
    - Kinsella, Katharine, 1889-1895, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2, Reel D98-D99)
    - Mac Knight, Dodge, 1893-1927, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Merriman, Daniel and Helen, 1898-1899 (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Nanna, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Paxton, William MacGregor, 1909-1930, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Perry, T. S., 1906-1914 (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Prellwitz, Henry and Angee, 1890-1932, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Redfield, Edward W., 1908-1915, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Reed, Ethel, 1896, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Richardson, Catherine and Dora, 1917-1922 (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Sherwin, Eleanor, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Smith, Maverette G. (with references to Hassam), 1898-1899, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Tarbell, Edmund C., circa 1900-1931, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Williams, Mary E., 1896-1897, undated (Box 2, Reel D99)
    - Zeffie, circa 1909-1917, undated (Box 2, Reel D100)
  - Business Correspondence, circa 1880-1935, 2.3:
    - Letters from Philip L. Hale, 1880-1930, undated (Box 2, Reel D100)
    - Letters to Philip L. Hale, 1880-1915, (6 folders) (Box 2, Reel D100)
    - Letters to Philip L. Hale, 1916-1935, undated, (8 folders) (Box 3, Reel D100-D101)
- Writings, circa 1923-1930, Series 3:; (Boxes 3-4, 1.0 linear ft.)
  Philip L. Hale's writings consist of short stories, poems, character sketches, articles, lectures and speeches, notes, and unidentified fragments. The manuscripts of Jan Vermeer of Delft and Hale's other monographs are not among the Philip Leslie Hale papers owned by the Archives of American Art.
  Hale was a well known lecturer. Notes and texts survive for many lectures on a variety of art topics. Some may have been used in the classroom, but it is likely that most were delivered at various venues arranged by a lecture bureau. The content of lectures delivered to his classes at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, are documented by Mrs. Nathan Hale's anatomy lecture notes and Anna Hunt's notes on history of art lectures.
  Some of Hale's earliest writings are among his boyhood notebooks in Series 1: Biographical Information. Published versions of his writings and lectures are among Series 5: Memorial Book, and Series 6: Printed Material.
  Also found in this series is one folder of poems by other authors.
  - Character Sketches, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Lectures on Anatomy (Notes by niece Mrs. Nathan Hale), undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Lectures on History of Art, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Reel D102)
  - Lectures and Miscellaneous documents concerning Lectures, 1923-1930, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel D102)
  - Lectures on Various Art Topics, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Reel D102)
  - Lists, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, undated, (includes handwritten manuscripts and typescripts; partially filmed; 2 folders) (Box 3, Reel D102)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1922, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Notes on Artists, undated (Box 3, Reel D101)
  - Notes on Esthetics and Philosophy, undated (Box 3, Reel D101)
  - Notes, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Play, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Poems, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
  - Political Writings, undated (Box 3, Reel D102)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 4, Reel D102)
  - Short Stories (A-Z by title and untitled), undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Poems by Other Authors, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
- Art Work, circa 1870, 1914, Series 4:; (Box 4; 0.25 linear ft.)
  In addition to artwork housed with this series, there are numerous sketches, mainly by Philip Leslie Hale, but a few by other hands, scattered throughout the collection. Some letters to and from Hale are illustrated. And a fair number of letters and other documents were used by Hale as handy pieces of paper for quick sketches.
  - Ink Sketches, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Oil Sketches, Landscapes, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Pastels, Figures and Landscapes, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Prints, Head and Figures, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Pencil Sketches, Anatomical Studies, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Pencil Sketches, Figures, Clothed, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Pencil Sketches, Landscapes and Miscellaneous Subjects, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1870 (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Watercolors, Landscapes and Figures, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Sketches and Print By Others, 1914, undated (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Sketchbooks, undated, (8 vols. in 2 folders) (Box 4, Reel D102)
  - Sketches: Heads, Figures, Anatomical Drawings, and Miscellaneous Subjects, undated (Box 4, Reel D102)
- Memorial Book, circa 1862-1962, Series 5:; (Boxes 4-6, 8, OV 9; 2.3 linear ft.)